Guide to the Forestvale Cemetery Association records 1890-1988
Montana Historical Society
Forestvale Cemetery Association records
1890-1988
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 240
Forestvale Cemetery Association (Helena, Mont.)
10 linear feet of shelf space
The Forestvale Cemetery Association operates a cemetery in Helena, Montana. Records (1890-1988) of the Association and its predecessor, the Helena Cemetery Association, include correspondence, financial records, legal documents, burial registers, minutes, maps, a card file, and lot books.
Historical Note:
The original Helena Cemetery Association was incorporated on June 11, 1887, by Andrew J. Fisk, Ansalem J. Davidson, William Muth, and others, in response to a lack of space available in existing cemeteries. A year later the Helena City Council appointed a committee to study the matter. In May 1890, after several years of considering various proposals for locations and facilities, F.R. Wallace, as trustee for the City of Helena, purchased the present site of the cemetery from Evan and Amelia Harris for $22,220. In August 1890 a second Helena Cemetery Association was incorporated by P.D. Grommon, John B. Clayberg, A.M. Thornburgh and E.C. Richards to acquire land; improve and beautify it; lay out and construct lots, roadways, and water systems; sell lots; and all other acts "connected with the maintenance and operation of a Cemetery..." The Association was incorporated for $250,000 and stockholders included many of the most prominent names in Helena society. One of the first acts of the new Association was to purchase the property for the cemetery from trustee F.R. Wallace, for "$1 and other valuable considerations" among which was the full $250,000 worth of capital stock. Wallace then transferred back to the Association $61,000 worth of stock to be sold as needed to finance improvements. One such improvement was a street railway to the site, constructed by Peter Winne. Under the leadership of Winne, who became President in December 1892, the association developed the site, installed a water system, planted trees and shrubs, and sold lots. A permanent Endowment Fund and a Perpetual Care and Improvement Fund were also established.
The Helena Cemetery was renamed the Forestvale Cemetery around 1901. The Helena Cemetery Association's corporate charter expired in 1910, but the affairs of the Association were never formally closed. The Association continued to meet until 1913. Secretary and Manager Henry Winter had by this time acquired, through direct ownership and proxies, control of over 99% of the stock. He assumed personal management of the property. In May 1918, in response to rapidly rising lot prices, poor maintenance, and accusations of mismanagement, William Muth and other trustees of the Permanent Care and Improvement Fund and Endowment Fund filed suit against Henry Winter and other trustees to force them to account for the funds. Muth and other lot owners and relatives of people buried in the cemetery met in June of 1919 to form a new association. They selected the name Forestvale Cemetery Association and proceeded to file a condemnation suit to force Winter to sell the property. The court eventually set the price at $35,000 and the property was conveyed to the Forestvale Cemetery Association. Over the years the endowment funds which were based on a percentage of the original lot purchase prices became inadequate to maintain the cemetery, which fell into serious disrepair.
In 1965 a concerted effort was made to clean up the grounds by removing excess trees and shrubs, improving the irrigation system, filling sunking plots, etc. However by the late 1980s the cemetery was again in poor condition. In a special election on April 2, 1991, School District #1 voted to fund a cemetery district to provide permanent upkeep by Lewis and Clark County.
Records. 1890-1988. 10 linear feet. Records of the Forestvale Cemetery Association, and its predecessor the Helena Cemetery Association, include correspondence (1891-1911, 1952-1988) regarding general operation of the Forestvale Cemetery, and with lot owners and relatives about burials and lot maintenance; court papers (1894-1978); financial records (1921-1982); legal documents (1890-1958) including abstracts of title, agreements, deeds, etc.; maps (1926-1981); minutes (1890-1913, 1919-1986); organizational records (1891-1986) including annual reports of corporations, bylaws, rules, certificate of incorporation, and miscellany; a subject file (1961-1964) on the sprinkler system; and miscellany (1890-1974). The miscellany series contains the real heart of the collection, consisting of burial index cards (1890s-1940s) including a section on Chinese burials, burial registers (1890-1971), a lot book (1890-1963), lot owner index cards (1890s-1940s), lot owners books (1890-1930), and miscellany. [Collection should be used in conjunction with the Forestvale Cemetery book compiled by the Lewis and Clark County Genealogical Society, in the catalogued Library Collection.]
Arranged by series. Some material housed in Archives Manuscript Volumes, Archives Map Case, and oversize boxes. See inventory below for more information.
Collection open for research..
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Forestvale Cemetery Association (Helena, Mont.)
Helena (Mont.)--Cemeteries; Montana--Genealogy
Cemeteries--Montana; Chinese--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Financial Records
  - Journal, 1970-1982 (Volume 1)
- Miscellany
  - Burial registers, No. 1-2 (includes name of deceased, place born, residence, date of death, cause of death, age of deceased, undertaker, lot owner, lot and section, and remarks), 1882-1930, 1930-1971 (Volume 2-3)
- Miscellany
  - Deed book, 1909-1921 (Volume 4)
- General Correspondence
  - A-Z (primarily with lot owners and relatives concerning burials, maintenance of lots, etc.), 1957-1974 (Box-folder 1 / 1-15)
  - Miscellaneous (re general operation of cemetery), 1891-1911, 1952-1988 (Box-folder 1 / 16-18)
- Court Papers
  - In re "The Helena Cemetery Association" and the Trustees of the "Permanent Care and Improvement Fund" and "Endowment Fund" of said Association, 1925 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - In the matter of I.O.O.F. Cemetery Association, 1969 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - In the matter of the Estate of Velma Weiss Spurlock, deceased, 1962 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - In the matter of the Forestvale Endowment Fund, 1974 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Montana National Bank vs. George S. VanLaw, et al. (re Helena Cemetery Association stock), 1894 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Eileen E. Richey vs. ... The Endowment Funds of the Forestvale Cemetery Association ..., 1978 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
- Financial Records
  - Accounts receivable [scattered], 1964-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Advance sales, 1965 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Audits, 1948-1960 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Bank books, cancelled checks, etc. [scattered], 1961-1983 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Donations, 1987 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Employee earning statements, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Employee timebook, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Endowment Fund and Permanent Care and Improvement Fund collections, 1921-1928, 1937-1945 (Box-folder 2 / 14-16)
  - Financial reports of Trustees of the Endowment Fund, Perpetual Care and Improvement Fund and John H. Shober Memorial Fund, 1936-1983 (Box-folder 2 / 17-19)
  - Financial statements, 1924-1930, 1959-1988 (Box-folder 2 / 20-21)
  - General ledger, 1929-1979 (Box-folder 3 / 1-3)
  - Gross sales, 1929-1933 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - Insurance policy, 1950 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
  - Journal, 1927-1928 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - General ledger [Oversize Box], 1921-1929 (Oversizebox-folder 4 / 1)
  - Journal [Oversize Box], 1921-1927 (Oversizebox-folder 4 / 2)
  - Journal [Oversize Box], 1940-1941 (Oversizebox-folder 4 / 3)
  - Journal [Oversize Box], 1941-1970 (Oversizebox-folder 5 / 1-3)
  - Monthly recapitulations and closing entries [Oversize Box], 1961-1963 (Oversizebox-folder 5 / 4)
  - Promissory note, 1933 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Return of organization exempt from income tax, 1965-1982 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
    RESTRICTED
  - Trial balance sheets [scattered], 1923-1934 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 6 / 4)
- Legal Documents
  - Abstracts of title (includes many court papers re the cases of Forestvale Cemetery Association against the Helena Cemetery Association and Henry Winter), 1890, 1931 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
  - Agreements, deeds, mortgages, 1890-1941 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
  - Conditional sale contracts: A-T, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
- Maps
  - Improvements of the Forestvale Cemetery, 1926 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
- Minutes
  - Minute book: Helena Cemetery Association, 1890-1913 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Minute book: Forestvale Cemetery Association (includes articles of incorporation, bylaws, financial statements, legal documents, etc.), 1934-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
- Organization
  - Annual meetings (includes correspondence, notices, agendas, proxies, and other material removed from minute book for preservation), 1899-1913, 1936-1986 (Box-folder 6 / 11-12)
  - Annual report of corporation, 1972, 1975 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
  - Bylaws and rules, 1922 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
  - Certificate of incorporation: Helena Cemetery Association [typescript copy], 1890 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
  - Reports to trustees, 1957, 1964 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1891-1898 (Box-folder 6 / 17)
- Subject File
  - Sprinkler system, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 6 / 18)
- Miscellany
  - Accident reports to Industrial Accident Board, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 6 / 19)
  - Associate membership lists, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 6 / 20)
- Minutes
  - Minute book: Forestvale Cemetery Association (includes articles of incorporation, bylaws, financial statements, legal documents, etc.), 1919-1934 (Oversizebox-folder 7 / 1)
- Miscellany
  - Burial index cards, A-Z, Chinese (includes name of person buried, date of burial, lot number and location, lot book page number, lot owners name), circa 1890-1949 (Cardbox 8-15)
- Miscellany
  - Burials in Woodlawn Section, 1884-1964 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
  - Endowed lot owners list (includes money paid in), 1923 (Box-folder 16 / 2)
  - "Forestvale Cemetery: a cemetery is hallowed ground" by M. Greenfield (re sale of land to Schroeder Brothers), 1964 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
  - Lot owners list (includes alphabetical list or owners, list by cemetery area, and list of veterans), 1908-1910 (Box-folder 16 / 4)
  - Lot owners list (includes alphabetical list or owners, with location of lot), undated (Box-folder 16 / 5)
  - Lot owners list (lists unpaid accounts), 1958-1974 (Box-folder 16 / 6)
  - Masonic Home of Montana minutes (includes report of Grand Lodge, A.F. and A.M. of Montana on proposed purchase of land for cemetery from Forestvale Cemetery Association), 1927 September 3 (Box-folder 16 / 7)
  - Pamphlet on perpetual card fund, undated (Box-folder 16 / 8)
- Clippings
  - Clippings (re original city council plans for cemetery, cemetery improvements, etc.), 1888, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 16 / 9)
- Miscellany
  - Lot owners index cards, A-Z (includes name of lot owner, lot section and number, and record of burials in lot), circa 1890-1949 (Box-folder 17 / 22)
  - Lot book (arranged by cemetery section and date of sale; includes purchaser's name, price, payments made, and remarks) [Oversize Box], 1890-1963 (Oversizebox-folder 23 / 1)
  - Lot owners index (includes a few notations of burials from the 1930s to the 1950s) [Oversize Box], 1890-1930 (Oversizebox-folder 23 / 2)
- Maps
  - Maps and drawings of Forestvale Cemetery [Oversize: See Archives Map Case], 1911, 1934, 1940, 1981, undated (Oversize-folder 1)